Finding Aid for Dorothy McCauley papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dorothy McCauley papers 1961-1989
Dorothy McCauley
1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
89498 Aa 2
Newsletters and minutes of executive committee of the Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council; newsletters of area block clubs; files relating to her community and organizational involvement; published materials; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was the gift of Mrs. Dorothy McCauley and the Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council, June 13, 1989. (Donor no. 7697 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dorothy McCauley, long-time resident of Detroit, Michigan, was organizer and executive director of the Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council, an association of businesses, church and school leaders, and block clubs in the area bounded by Davison, Joy, Linwood, and Dexter in northwest Detroit. Founded in 1961, the Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council is a "non-partisan, civic organization dedicated to maintaining, improving and developing the area as a better place to live." The Council has involved itself with youth, senior citizen, recreation, health, welfare, education, and other local and civic programs. The Council has been especially concerned with matters of home improvement and neighborhood development. With money received from the city of Detroit's Neighborhood Opportunity Fund, McCauley as head of the Council's Non-Profit Housing Corporation worked to coordinate the screening and contracting of senior citizen home repairs. McCauley was ever vigilant about the kinds of businesses wanting to operate in her neighborhood, using the influence of the Council to circulate petitions addressed to Detroit Common Council urging them to deny requests of individuals wanting to establish arcades, a methadone treatment center, and other "seedy, slum-inducing businesses" that had been uprooted from the city's downtown because of urban renewal.
The McCauley collection consists of the records of the Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council but including as well files documenting McCauley's other community activities. Of most importance in understanding the work of the Council are its News Bulletins which date from 1960 to 1989. In addition to neighborhood news, the bulletins included notes about city government, particularly as they related to this local neighborhood. The News Bulletins were also the place where McCauley informed the community about the Council's various petition drives.
As executive secretary of the Council, McCauley wanted her group to act as a clearinghouse of information about matters of neighborhood concern. Her collection reflects this interest. Besides material about the Council, McCauley also preserved records about the various block clubs that made up the Council. The great bulk of these relate to the Dexter-Elmhurst Advisory Board, but there are also newsletters for the Glynn Court Block Club and the Calvert Civic Block Club.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Citizens' associations--Michigan--Detroit.; Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); McCauley, Dorothy.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Children.
Subjects-Visual Material:
African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Children.; Photographs.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Community Council
  - Constitution and bylaws and descriptive information (Box 1)
  - Executive Board and Council minutes (Box 1)
  - News Bulletins
    - 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
    - Fragments (Box 1)
  - Petitions to Detroit City Council (and other city agencies) (Box 1)
  - Chronological file
    - 1961-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Administrative miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Dav-Joy-Lin-Dex Non-profit Housing Corporation, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  - All Sales Advisory Committee (Box 1)
  - Block Clubs
    - Calvert City Block Club (Box 1)
    - Dexter Elmhurst Community Advisory Board
      - Agendas (Box 1)
      - Minutes,1978-1989 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Glynn Court Block Club (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Community Screening Committee (Box 2)
  - Detroit Association of Black Organizations (Box 2)
  - Kirwood General Hospital (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Detroit Anti-Crime Coalition (Box 2)
  - Police-community relations (Box 2)
- Published materials
  - Published materials (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The photographs series consist of a folder of color snapshots of African American children in Detroit, Michigan, and a neighborhood youth center.
  - Photographs (Box 2)